A Guide to the West Virginia Vital Statistics compiled by the Virginia Dept. of Health, 1853-1863
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the West Virginia Vital Statistics compiled by the Virginia Dept. of Health 1853-1863
The Library of Virginia
38788
42 cu. ft. (28 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Details of acquisition unknown.
Alternative Form Available
Available on microfilm. Please note: the original materials from which the microfilm was created are in extremely poor condition. The microfilm represents the best image that can be achieved considering the condition of the original records.
Biographical Information
The Medical Society of Virginia, formed in 1870, sponsored a bill to create a State Board of Health and Vital Statistics to supervise sanitation matters and to prevent the spread of contagious diseases. This bill was enacted into law by the General Assembly on February 13, 1872, but no funding was provided the Board, which functioned intermittently until 1896. The General Assembly passed an act on March 3, 1896, establishing and funding the Board of Health. An act passed on March 7, 1900, created local boards of health in every country and city and gave the State Board authority over them.
The position of Commissioner of Health was established as the executive officer of the Board of Health by an act of the General Assembly passed on March 14, 1908. The State Government Reorganization Act passed by the General Assembly on April 18, 1927, created the Department of Health under the aegis of the State Board of Health.
The Department serves as the administrative arm of the Board of Health under the supervision of the State Health Commissioner and is responsible to the Secretary of Health and Human Resources. It continues to exercise its major functions of controlling sanitation problems and limiting the spread of communicable diseases through a "comprehensive program of preventative, curative, restorative, and environmental health services." It is also responsible for the education of the public in matters of health, the keeping of vital records and health statistics, the licensure of health facilities, and the general protection of the public health. The Department of Health includes the following offices: Center for Quality Health Care, Office of Emergancy Medical Services, Environmental Helath Services, Epidemiology, Family Health Services, Medical Examiner, Primary Care, Vital Records, Vital Statistics, and Water Programs.
The state of West Virginia was formed on 13 May 1862 and consisted of the following fifty counties that were formerly in Virginia: Barbour, Berkeley, Boone, Braxton, Brooke, Cabell, Calhoun, Clay, Doddridge, Fayette, Gilmer, Greenbrier, Hampshire, Hancock, Hardy, Harrison, Jackson, Jefferson, Kanawha, Lewis, Logan, Marion, Marshall, Marion, McDowell, Mercer, Monongalia, Monroe, Morgan, Nicholas, Ohio, Pendleton, Pleasants, Pocahontas, Preston, Putnam, Raleigh, Randolph, Ritchie, Roane, Taylor, Tucker, Tyler, Upshur, Wayne, Webster, Wetzel, Wirt, Wood and Wyoming.
Scope and Content
Contains registers of births, deaths and marriages of counties in Virginia that were later incorporated into West Virginia in 1863. Birth Registers include: date of birth, name, color, and sex of the child, place of birth, father's name, occupation and residence, name of mother, any deformities or circumstances of interest, and the source of the information. Death registers include: full name, race, and sex of the deceased, date, place and cause of death, name of parents, birthdate and occupation of the deceased, name of the coroner and the source of the information. Marriage registers include: date and place of the marriage, full names of husband and wife, age and condition, place of their births, place of residence, names of their parents, occupations, and the name of the person performing the ceremony.
Unfortunately, most of these records are incomplete with gaps in coverage from county to county. In particular, please note that the birth registers for McDowell County are absent from the collection.
Note that some of the documents are in poor condition, including illegible text due to faded ink.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by county and then alphabetically by type of record.
Contents List
- Barbour County Births 1854-1860 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Barbour County Deaths 1854-1858, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Barbour County Marriages 1853-1859 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Berkeley County Births 1853-1860 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Berkeley County Deaths 1853-1860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Berkeley County Marriages 1854-1860 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Boone County Births, 1853-1859 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Boone County Deaths 1853-1859 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Boone County Marriages 1853, 1855-1860 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Braxton County Births 1853-1854 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Braxton County Deaths 1853-1854, 1856-1859 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Braxton County Marriages 1854-1860 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Brooke County Births 1853, 1855, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Brooke County Death Records 1853, 1856-1859 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Brooke County Marriage Records 1854-1860 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Cabell County Birth Records 1854-1856 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Cabell County Death Records 1854, 1855, 1857-1859 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Cabell County Marriage Records 1853-1855, 1857-1860 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Calhoun Birth Records 1855-1859 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Calhoun County Death Records 1855-1859 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Calhoun County Marriage Records 1856-1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Clay County Birth Records 1859-1860 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Clay County Death Records 1858-1860 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Clay County Marriage Records 1856-1858 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Doddridge County Birth Records 1854-1859 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Doddridge County Death Records 1854-1858 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Doddridge County Marriage Records 1855-1860 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Fayette County Birth Records 1854-1859 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Fayette County Death Records 1854-1859 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Fayette County Marriage Records 1854-1860 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Gilmer County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Gilmer County Death Records 1854, 1856-1857, 1859 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Gilmer County Marriage Records 1853-1855, 1856-1858, 1860 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Greenbrier County Birth Records 1853-1862 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Greenbrier County Death Records 1853-1862 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Greenbrier County Marriage Records 1854-1858, 1860-1862 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Hampshire County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Hampshire County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Hampshire County Marriage Records 1854-1857, 1859-1860 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Hancock County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Hancock County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Hancock County Marriage Records 1854-1857, 1859-1860 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Hardy County Birth Records 1853-1860 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Hardy County Death Records 1853-1860 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Hardy County Marriage Records 1854-1858, 1860 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Harrison County Birth Records 1855-1859, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Harrison County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Harrison County Marriage Records 1854-1856, 1859-1861, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Jackson County Birth Records 1854-1859 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Jackson County Death Records 1854-1859 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Jackson County Marriage Records 1854-1860 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Jefferson County Birth Records 1853-1860 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Jefferson County Death Records 1853-1860 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Jefferson County Marriage Records 1854-1858, 1860 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Kanawha County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Kanawha County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Kanawha County Marriage Records 1853-1858, 1860 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Lewis County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Lewis County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Lewis County Marriage Records 1853-1860 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Logan County Birth Records 1853-1860 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Logan County Death Records 1853-1860 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Logan County Marriage Records 1853-1860 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Marion County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Marion County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Marion County Marriage Records 1853-1860 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Marshall County Birth Records 1854-1859 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Marshall County Death Records 1853-1858, 1860 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Marshall County Marriage Records 1854-1858, 1860 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Mason County Birth Records 1853-1859, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Mason County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Mason County Marriage Records 1853-1857, 1860 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- McDowell County Death Records 1858 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- McDowell County Marriage Records 1858-1860, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Mercer County Birth Records 1853, 1855-1860 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Mercer County Death Records 1853, 1855-1860 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Mercer County Marriage Records 1854-1861 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Monongalia County Birth Records 1854-1859, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Monongalia County Death Records 1853-1859, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Monongalia County Marriage Records 1854-1855, 1857-1860 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Monroe County Birth Records 1853, 1855-1860, 1862 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Monroe County Death Records 1853-1860, 1862 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Monroe County Marriage Records 1854-1858, 1860-1861 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Morgan County Birth Records 1853-1857 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Morgan County Death Records 1853-1857 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Morgan County Marriage Records 1854-1858 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Nicholas County Birth Records 1854, 1856-1859 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Nicholas County Death Records 1853-1855, 1857-1859 (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Nicholas County Marriage Records 1853-1860 (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Ohio County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Ohio County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Ohio County Marriage Records 1854-1859 (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Pendleton County Birth Records 1853-1854, 1856-1860, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Pendleton County Death Records 1854, 1857-1858, 1860, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Pendleton County Marriage Records 1854-1857, 1860 (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Pleasants County Birth Records 1853-1860, undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Pleasants County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 19, Folder 5)
- Pendleton County Marriage Records, 1854-1857, 1860 (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Pocahontas County Birth Records 1853-1860, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
- Pocahontas County Death Records 1853-1860 (Box 19, Folder 8)
- Pocahontas County Marriage Records 1854-1858, 1860 (Box 19, Folder 9)
- Preston County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Preston County Death Records 1853-1860 (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Preston County Marriage Records 1853-1860 (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Putnam County Birth Records 1853-1859, undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
- Putnam County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 21, Folder 2)
- Putnam County Marriage Records 1853-1858, 1861 (Box 21, Folder 3)
- Raleigh County Birth Records 1853-1860 (Box 21, Folder 4)
- Raleigh County Death Records 1853-1860 (Box 21, Folder 5)
- Raleigh County Marriage Records 1854-1860 (Box 21, Folder 6)
- Randolph County Birth Records 1853-1859, undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Randolph County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 22, Folder 2)
- Randolph County Marriage Records 1854-1859 (Box 22, Folder 3)
- Ritchie County Birth Records 1853-1860, undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
- Ritchie County Death Records 1853-1857, 1859-1860 (Box 22, Folder 5)
- Ritchie County Marriage Records 1854-1861, undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
- Roane County Birth Records 1856-1859 (Box 23, Folder 1)
- Roane County Death Records 1856, 1858-1859 (Box 23, Folder 2)
- Roane County Marriage Records 1856-1858, undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
- Taylor County Birth Records 1853-1859, undated (Box 23, Folder 4)
- Taylor County Death Records 1854-1859 (Box 23, Folder 5)
- Taylor County Marriage Records 1853-1860 (Box 23, Folder 6)
- Tucker Cuonty Birth Records 1856-1859 (Box 24, Folder 1)
- Tucker County Death Records 1856-1859 (Box 24, Folder 2)
- Tucker County Marriage Records 1856-1860 (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Tyler County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 24, Folder 4)
- Tyler County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 24, Folder 5)
- Tyler County Marriage Records 1854-1860, undated (Box 24, Folder 6)
- Upshur County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 25, Folder 1)
- Upshur County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 25, Folder 2)
- Upshur County Marriage Records 1854-1860 (Box 25, Folder 3)
- Wayne County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 25, Folder 4)
- Wayne County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 25, Folder 5)
- Wayne County Marriage Records 1854-1860 (Box 25, Folder 6)
- Webster County Birth Records 1860 (Box 25, Folder 7)
- Webster County Death Records 1859-1860 (Box 25, Folder 8)
- Webster County Marriage Records 1860 (Box 25, Folder 9)
- Wetzel County Birth Records 1854-1860, undated (Box 26, Folder 1)
- Wetzel County Death Records 1853-1854, 1856-1859, undated (Box 26, Folder 2)
- Wetzel County Marriage Records, 1854-1855, 1857-1860, undated (Box 26, Folder 3)
- Wirt County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 26, Folder 4)
- Wirt County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 26, Folder 5)
- Wirt County Marriage Records 1854-1860 (Box 26, Folder 6)
- Wood County Birth Records 1853-1859 (Box 27, Folder 1)
- Wood County Death Records 1853-1859 (Box 27, Folder 2)
- Wood County Marriage Records 1853-1860 (Box 27, Folder 3)
- Wyoming County Birth Records 1853-1860 (Box 27, Folder 4)
- Wyoming County Death Records 1853-1860 (Box 5)
- Wyoming County Marriage Records 1854-1860 (Box 27, Folder 6)
- Fragments undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
- Fragments undated (Box 28, Folder 2)
- Fragments undated (Box 28, Folder 3)